<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Basket</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="/basket/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/basket" />
<updated>2015-09-21T21:34:47-04:00</updated>
<id>/basket/</id>
<author>
  <name></name>
  <uri>/basket/</uri>
  
</author>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Case Study: Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/basket/articles/Haiti-HOT/" />
  <id>/basket/articles/Haiti-HOT</id>
  <published>2015-04-18T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2015-04-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>HOT OSM</name>
    <uri>/basket</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://felix.delattre.de/weblog/2015/04/18/case-study-humanitarian-openstreetmap-team&quot;&gt;HOTOSM CASE STUDY IN HAITI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team is based on the principle that “free map data would be a tremendous benefit for humanitarian aid and economic development” (OSM wiki about HOT, visited 26th of March 2015) and the main activity are the organization of activations of worldwide volunteers to collaborate all together over the OpenStreetMap platform to raise geographic data for disaster response after natural catastrophes (such as the recent Ebola outbreak 2014, the tsunami 2013 in the Philippines or the earthquake in Haiti 2010). This information is then freely available for everybody but in particular to organizations and government working in the field to safe people’s life and improve the situation on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/basket/articles/Haiti-HOT/&quot;&gt;Case Study: Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;/basket&quot;&gt;Basket&lt;/a&gt; on April 18, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Volcano Mapping in Indonesia]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/basket/articles/Indonesia/" />
  <id>/basket/articles/Indonesia</id>
  <published>2015-04-07T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2015-04-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>George Mason University</name>
    <uri>/basket</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Excerpt from George Mason University’s Mason News&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full article: &lt;a href=&quot;https://newsdesk.gmu.edu/2015/04/map-off-unites-regional-community-for-humanitarian-effort/&quot;&gt;Map-Off Unites Regional Community for Humanitarian Effort&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Imagine working on projects intended to provide health care to remote villages in Africa, assist with volcano eruption preparedness and mitigation plans in East Asia, or minimize the impact of natural disasters around the world, from your own computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CmdrKerfy/basket/gh-pages/images/ind-volcano/gmu.jpg&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/CmdrKerfy/basket/gh-pages/images/ind-volcano/gmu2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Photo Credit: Mason News&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;More than  120 citizen scientists, including students and local community volunteers from across the region, did just that and more during a March 27 “Map-Off” co-hosted at the George Mason University and George Washington University campuses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/basket/articles/Indonesia/&quot;&gt;Volcano Mapping in Indonesia&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;/basket&quot;&gt;Basket&lt;/a&gt; on April 07, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[The first French collaborative National Address Database is now online, and freely accessible.]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/basket/articles/Etalab/" />
  <id>/basket/articles/Etalab</id>
  <published>2015-03-16T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2015-03-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Etalab</name>
    <uri>/basket</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/basket/articles/Etalab/&quot;&gt;The first French collaborative National Address Database is now online, and freely accessible.&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;/basket&quot;&gt;Basket&lt;/a&gt; on March 16, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[OSM for Malaria Eradication in Botswana]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/basket/articles/Botswana/" />
  <id>/basket/articles/Botswana</id>
  <published>2015-03-01T00:00:00-05:00</published>
  <updated>2015-03-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Peace Corps</name>
    <uri>/basket</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/basket/assets/OSM_Malaria.pdf&quot;&gt;BOSTWANA CASE STUDY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A brief case study written by Peace Corps’ Mike Banfield and Theresa Govert, currently stationed in Botswana. The Peace Corps worked with volunteers from the local health clinic to use GPS devices, OSM and QGIS to analyze the effectiveness of a malaria prevention campaign. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a model case for how Peace Corps volunteers and their communities can take advantage of GIS tools to make data-driven project decisions.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/basket/articles/Botswana/&quot;&gt;OSM for Malaria Eradication in Botswana&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;/basket&quot;&gt;Basket&lt;/a&gt; on March 01, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[GIS Support for the MSF Ebola response in Guinea]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/basket/articles/Ebola-GIS/" />
  <id>/basket/articles/Ebola-GIS</id>
  <published>2014-07-01T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2014-07-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>MSF</name>
    <uri>/basket</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/basket/assets/MSF_Ebola.pdf&quot;&gt;EBOLA GIS CASE STUDY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2014, MSF-Switzerland deployed a dedicated Geographic 
Information Systems (GIS) officer to Guinea in response to the Ebola 
outbreak in the south of the country. In support of the epidemiological team, 
the GIS officer was charged with producing general overview maps, as well 
as topical maps that supported different aspects of the operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the eight weeks of his mission, the GIS officer produced 109 maps 
for this previously very poorly mapped area. The maps included basic 
orientation maps that showed roads, landmarks and villages but also 
specialised maps that visualized population density or the spread of the 
disease. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both field and headquarters staff interviewed for this case study emphasized 
that having a dedicated GIS officer in the field was a major asset that had 
a significant positive impact on the operation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Universally, interviewees identified two outputs as the most useful: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Localization:&lt;/strong&gt; With the help of a newly created database and 
subsequently produced maps, the GIS officer was able to pinpoint the 
exact location of villages and identify villages that had the same name 
but were in different parts of the prefecture. Based on this information, 
MSF programme staff were able to respond to the outbreak faster, in 
a more targeted way and with fewer resources.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visualization:&lt;/strong&gt; A weekly mapping of confirmed and suspected Ebola 
cases helped translate the progression of the epidemic from technical 
data into an easy-to-grasp map. As a result, staff at all levels had a 
better understanding of the emergency.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interviews also highlighted the fact that most MSF staff know very little 
about GIS in general, let alone how a GIS officer could support them. The 
newly formed GIS unit at the Operational Centre Geneva (OCG) needs to 
do more to educate staff at headquarters and in the field about how GIS 
can support operations. For field deployments, this means that GIS officers 
need to be service-oriented self-starters because only very few staff will 
know how to make best use of his or her skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To map the areas of operation in a reasonable amount of time, the GIS 
unit - in support of the field officer - crowdsourced tasks that were neither 
confidential nor sensitive. As a result, a substantial number of overview maps were created with the help of close to 250 online volunteers. These 
volunteers helped to map previously unmapped cities and roads within 
a few days, and at a granular level, mapping individual buildings. These 
overview maps then became the foundation of many maps that the GIS 
officer created for the response. While the cooperation with the online 
volunteers was overall very positive, it also showed that coordination as 
well as expectation management can be improved. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the universally positive feedback about the GIS officer’s deployment, 
it is recommended that headquarters makes GIS officers available to field 
offices, where direct contact with field operations can bring clear benefits, 
and where close and timely monitoring of the spread of an epidemic is 
essential.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/basket/articles/Ebola-GIS/&quot;&gt;GIS Support for the MSF Ebola response in Guinea&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;/basket&quot;&gt;Basket&lt;/a&gt; on July 01, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>

</feed>
